اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝
بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله  وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
We talked about the Islam, of Sydina(سيدنا) Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
We talked about his Daw'ah(دعوة).
We talked about the trials, he went through.
Now, Rasool Allah ﷺ has given the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم permission to leave Makkah.
Whoever wants to leave and go to Al-Habasha(الحبشه), Abyssinia, you're free to go.
Because the persecution was reaching to a limit where it was becoming very difficult to handle.
And with all of the Sabr(صبر) of the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم and their patience,
but Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to make a way out for them.
So he gave them permission to go to Abyssinia, and many did.
Among the ones, who stayed behind was Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه who wanted to remain with his beloved,
but then he decided that he also has to leave for Abyssinia.
So he travels, out of Makkah and he reaches a few days, distance away from Makkah.
And he reaches a place called Barq-Ul-Ghamaad(برق الغماد),
where he meets with Ibn Dughanna(ابن دغنه), who was the leader of Al-Qara(القاره), a tribe called Al-Qara(القاره).
Ibn Dughanna(ابن دغنه) told Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه, Where are you heading.?
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(ابوبكرالصديق) said:
أخرجني قومي فَأريدو أن أخرُجَ في الأرض أسيحو فيها وَأعبُدالله
He said: My people have driven me out of my land.
So, I want to travel and worship Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
I'm going to travel in the earth, the earth belongs to Allah
ألأرض لله
And I'm going to worship Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
Ibn Dughanna(ابن دغنه) responded by saying and keep in mind this is a man who's not from Makkah.
But he knows Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), he heard about Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), he said:
يا أبابكر إنَّا مِثلك لا يَخرجُ ولا يُخرج،
فَإنَّك تَكسب المعدوم، وتصل الرحم
وتقرض ضعيف، وتعينو على نوائل بالحق ، فاَنَ جعارلَّك
He said: A man like you of your status, it's not appropriate for him to leave his land,
nor is it appropriate for him, to be driven out.
Because you are a man, who assists the needy and is kind towards his kinship
and you are generous towards the guest.
And you support the poor, and you stand up for every good cause.
Therefore go back and I will give you my protection.
There was a system in Arabia called Al-Ijarah(ألإجاره)
where you provide protection for somebody.
The rules of this system is that if I have a status in my people and I'm a leader of a clan
I can give protection for someone.
Now, the rule is: Is that I do not allow that to be violated even if it's going to cost me my life.
Therefore, the people used to honor the Ijarah(اجارة)
because they know that there's gonna be blood that is spilled, if there's a violation of the protection.
So, Ibn Dughanna(ابن دغنه) taking that position shows you, how much respect he had to Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) when he was Mushrik(مشرك),
I mean Ibn Dughanna(ابن دغنه) was a Mushrik(مشرك), he wasn't a Muslim
but the reputation of Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) was so high and everybody knew about it.
That Ibn Dughanna(ابن دغنه) was willing to give Ijarah(إجارة) to Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
Now keep in mind that usually people from outside Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
would not give Ijarah(اجارة) to somebody from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
because Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) are seen as the highest.
Therefore, they didn't see it appropriate for them to give Ijarah(اجارة) for somebody from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
But Ibn Dughanna(ابن دغنه) was willing to risk that
and he went ahead and took Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) into Makkah and said:
I am giving him my protection.
Now the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), they came to Ibn Dughanna(ابن دغنه) and they said:
We're not gonna violate your protection, however
we want you to make a condition on Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) that he prays at home.
We do not want him to pray publicly outside of his home.
Because if he does that, then he will deceive our women and our children.
So make him pray at home, we will honor your protection.
Ibn Dughanna(ابن دغنه) went to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and said: This is the agreement.
Do you accept Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).? He said: Yes I accept!
So now Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه would only pray at home.
After some time passed, you know this was against the habit of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه,
I mean, he's the one who asked for the proclamation of the message, in the first place.
He's the one who went to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said:
نَستَعْلَنْ
We want to publicly proclaim Islam.
So, for him, praying at home was not something that he was used to,
he used to always do it in public in front of everyone.
So he decided that in order not to break the agreement that he made with Ibn Dughanna(ابن دغنه).
He should pray in the front yard of his house.
So He's still within the house, but it's public.
So now, Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه would be praying in his front yard
and Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) was described as having a very soft heart
whenever he would recite the Ayat(آية) of Qur'an he would cry, tears would roll down his cheek.
And that's why, when Rasool Allah ﷺ told, he said that Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) should lead the people in Salah(صلاة).
Ayesha رضي الله عنها, she said that my father has a very soft heart and if he prays, he would cry.
So have Umar(عمر) pray.
So that was the Salah(صلاة) of Abu Bakr As-Siddique(ابوبكرالصديق), he would come to tears, very fast.
So Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه would be praying in his front yard
and all of the children and women and youth would come and gather and just watch Abu Bakr As-Siddique(ابوبكرالصديق) praying.
It was a very impressive scene.
So the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) got angry because they know the power of Salah(صلاة).
They know that Salah(صلاة), if the people see it, if they see somebody praying true Salah(صلاة) with Khushoo(خشوع),
that this would attract them to Islam.
So they went to Ibn Dughanna(ابن دغنه) and they said:
Our agreement with you was that he doesn't pray publicly.
So, Ibn Dughanna(ابن دغنه) goes to Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه and says:
Listen the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) are not gonna allow you to do this
so you either go back and pray in your room,
otherwise you hand me over my protection.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said:
I'm handing you over my protection and I'm happy with the protection of Allah.
أرضى بِجَوارالله
I'm happy with the protection of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
You remember yesterday when you talked about the test of Allah to Az-Zunairah(الزنيره),
when Allah took away her sight to test her Eeman(ايمان).
Well the same thing happened to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) as soon as the Ijarah(اجارة) was ended, the protection was ended
and he went to pray in front of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) publicly.
One of Sufaha Al-Quraish(سفها القريش), one of the ignorant among Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) came and hit Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
So Abu Bakr As-Siddique(ابوبكرالصديق) was speaking to Al-Waleed Bin Mugheera(الوليدبن مغيره), he's saying:
Can't you see what this ignorant man is doing?
Al-Mugheera(المغيره) said: You are the one, who brought it on yourself.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) would only say,
ربي إنك حليم ، ربي ما أحلمك، ربي ما أحلمك
O Allah, You're so compassionate and merciful.
He was beaten up, but he would say,
O Allah, you are very compassionate and merciful, Al-Hamdolillah(الحمدلله).
You know, we praise Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ for everything.
If something good happens, we say Al-Hamdolillah(الحمدلله).
If something bad happens we say, Al-Hamdolillah(الحمدلله) it's all from Allah.
We are property of Allah, He has the right to do with us whatever He wants.
We talked about the knowledge of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه, to what it's called Fiqh Al-Waqiah(فقه الواقع), the current affairs.
He knew about the different tribes, qualities.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ took him along with him, to introduce himself to the tribes in Hajj(حج).
Because that's when all of the tribes gather.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ would go around to the different tribes
offering Islam to them, and asking them for protection, An-Nusra(النصره).
And Rasool Allah ﷺ did that for a very long time.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was looking for An-Nusra(النصره), protection for the religion.
So he would take along with him, Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
Now this story that I'm going to mention was narrated by Ali Bin Abi Talib رضي الله عنه.
Ali Bin Abi Talib(علي بن ابي طالب) said: We were visiting the different tribes in their camps.
So, we came to this tribe Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه was a spokesman.
He went and he asked them, where are you from.?
They said: From Rabiyah(ربيعة)
He said: From which part of Rabiyah(ربيعه).?
They said;
من هامته العظمى
He said: Which part of Haam Ma Tal Uzma(هامته العظمى).?
They said: From Dahal Al-Akbar(دهل الاكبر).
Now, Rabiyah(ربيعة) is a tribe in Iraq, and the sub tribe is Haam Ma Tal Uzma(هامته العظمى),
which means the great forehead.
And then Dahal Al-Akbar(دهل الاكبر) means, Dahal(دهل) the Great.
So there's Dahal(دهل) the great, and there's Dahal(دهل) the small.
And it's a very fine line between these tribes because they all fall under Rabiyah(ربيعة).
So they said Dahal Al-Akbar(دهل الاكبر) from the great Dahal(دهل)
which is kind of a proud name, the great Dahal(دهل).
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said;
Well than is Auf(عوف) the man, whose said, there's no free man in his Valley does he belong to you?
They said: No
He said: What about Al-Haufazaan(الحوفضان) Qatil Ul Malook(قاتل الملوك)
the one who would kill the kings.
Does he belong to you.? They said: No
He said: What about Al-Muzdaliff(مزدلف) Sahib Al-Imam Al-Mufradah(مفرده)
Al-Muzdalaf(المزدلف), who had the unique turban.
Does he belong to you.?
They said: No
He said: What about, are you the maternal uncle's of the Kings of Kinda(كنده).?
Then are you the relatives of the kings of Lakham(لخم),
They said: No
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said:
Then you are not from the great Dahal(دهل), you are from the small Dahal(دهل).
You don't belong to the great Dahal(دهل), you belong to the small Dahal(دهل).
And look at the questions that he was asking,
it shows the detailed knowledge that Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه had.
So, Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه was gonna leave
but a young man they say, who just started to grow a beard he was very young in age.
He came to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and he grabbed his camel
and he said: You asked us and we responded.
Now it's our turn to ask, and you respond.
Where are you from.?
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said: I'm from Quraish(قريش).
He said: Well then you are our leaders, I mean they all recognized Quraish(قريش).
What part of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) are you from? He said: From Tame Bin Murah(تيم بن مرة).
Tame(تيم) in Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) is seen as a very small and weak clan
it's not among the larger ones, like Bannu Hashim(بنوهاشم), the family of Rasool Allah ﷺ
or Bannu Makhzoom(بنومخزوم), the family of Khalid Bin Waleed(خالد بن وليد),
these were the great families or Bannu Umayyah(بنوامية).
So, Bannu Tame(بنوتيم) were very small in number and in the tribal society, your strength depends on your numbers.
So, Tame(تيم) was a very small branch of Quraish(قريش).
So, when this young man heard Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) say, I am from Tame(تيم)
he said, you've shown the target shooter where to shoot.
Meaning this is my opportunity to now ask you questions. He said:
Does Qusae Bin Kulaab(قصئي بن كلاب), the one who defeated all of the invaders who wanted to invade Makkah
and brought in Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) and unified them, and therefore he was called the unifier.
Is he from your people.?
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said: No
He said: What about Abd Manaaf(عبد المناف) who inherited everything from his father, is he from your people?
He said: No
What about Amr Bin Abd Manaf(عمرو بن عبد مناف)
the one who used to crush bread in the soup for the pilgrims, and was called Hashem(هاشم).
Are you from his people? He said: No
What about a Shaibat El-Hamd(شيبة الحمد), Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب).
The one, who used to feed the animals in the land and the birds in the sea
the man whom if you see his face is like the moon in the dark night.
Are you from his family.?
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) said: No
And then he asked him, then are you from the people of Ifadha(افاده) the ones, who take care of Al-Hajj(الحج).?
He said: No!
Are you the people of Hijaba(حجابه), the ones who have the key to Al-Ka'aba(الكعبه)
He said: No
Are you from the people of Nadwa(ندوه), the leadership of Quraish(قريش), the council?
Are you from the people, who provide the pilgrims with water.
He said: No
Are you from the people, who feed the pilgrims.?
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه was getting agitated with all of these questions
that he has to say: No
So, he pulled away his camel, and he walked, he just left the young man
because it was becoming a bit embarrassing.
So the young man smiled and he said:
صادفه در السيلي درًا يدفع فتارةً يذهبه’ وتارةً يصدع
It's a line poetry that he applied to this situation.
He said: Your stream was overcome by my river
that breaks it once and overrides it, another time.
Meaning - You prove that we are from Dahal Al-Asghar(دهل الاصغر)
and if you would have waited I would have showed you, where you belong to?
Rasool Allah ﷺ, he saw this and he laughed.
Ali Bin Abi Talib(علي بن ابي طالب) came to Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه and said:
لقدوقع العرابي منك على باقية
This Bedouin turned out to be a disaster for you.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said: Yes
For every problem there's a greater problem and our problems are caused by what we say.
I'm the one who got myself into this trouble, in the first place.
So then they moved on to another campground.
Abu Bakr As-Siddiqueرضي الله عنه appointed to them and said:
هَا أولآء غرورٌ الناس
These are great people.
So let's go to them.
So, they went there and these were from Bannu Shaibaan(بنوشعيبان)
Bannu Shaibaan(بنوشعيبان) are also tribe from Iraq.
And by the way, Imam Ahmad Bin Hanbal(امام احمد بن حنبل) is from Bannu Shaibaan(بنوشعيبان)
Imam Ahmad Bin Hanbal Shaibani(امام احمد بن حنبل ألشعيباني).
So they went to Bannu Shaibaan(بنوشعيبان)
and their leaders were there, Mafrooq(مفروق) and Hani Bin Qubaisa(هاني بن قبيسه)
and An-Nouman Bin Shuraik(النعمان بن شريق) and Musanna Bin Harissa Shaibani(مثنى بن حارثه شعيباني),
who later became one of the great generals in the Muslim armies.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه again notice that Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) is the one who's doing the speaking
not Muhammadﷺ, he was his spokesman.
He was the spokesperson of Muhammadﷺ.
So, Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) walked up to them
and then he asked Mafrooq(مفروق), who was the closest one to him.
He asked him, How large is your fighting force?
He said: One Thousand
Which was a large number in the desert. He said:
وكيف المنع فيكم
And how good is your protection?
He said: We do our best.
He then asked him, and what are the results of your wars against your enemies?
He said, or actually, before that he asked him,
he said: How strong are you in war?
Mafrooq(مفروق) responded by saying, we prefer our horses over our children
and we prefer our weapons over our camels.
He said: So, what are the results of your wars with your enemies?
He said: It is Allah, Who gives victory.
One day we win, one day we lose.
Because of these questions this man thought that the one was asking might be Muhammadﷺ.
Because they heard about Muhammadﷺ and they knew that he's looking for protection
and that's where all of these questions were leading to.
So he said:
لعلك اخى قريش
Are you the man from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)?
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said;
If you are referring to the Messenger of Allah, Muhammadﷺ, This is him.
And he pointed to Muhammadﷺ.
Mafrooq(مفروق) responded by saying;
We heard that he claims to be the Messenger of Allah.
So, the news of Muhammadﷺ even though, they didn't see him yet
the news of Muhammadﷺ has spread all the way to Iraq.
So, Mafrooq(مفروق) now, turned to Muhammad صلوات الله وسلام عليه and said;
إلى ماذا تدعو
What is your message?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: My message is to call to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, that there is no one worthy of worship, but Him.
And that I am the messenger of Allah, صلى الله عليه وسلم.
And, and he went on reciting some Ayaat(آيات), from Surat Al-An'aam(سورة الانعام)
that talk about the virtues of Islam
and some things that were Halal(حلال) and some things that were Haram(حرام).
They were very impressed with the Ayaat(آيات) of Qur'an, so they wanted to hear more.
He said: Tell me more. So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
إِنَّ ٱللَّهَ يَأْمُرُ بِٱلْعَدْلِ وَٱلْإِحْسَٰنِ وَإِيتَائِ ذِى ٱلْقُرْبَىٰ
وَيَنْهَىٰ عَنِ ٱلْفَحْشَاءِ وَٱلْمُنكَرِ وَٱلْبَغْىِ ۚ يَعِظُكُمْ لَعَلَّكُمْ تَذَكَّرُونَ
Mafrooq(مفروق) said: What you have called to, is a very noble message
and the people, who have treated you in an evil way are truly evil people.
If this is your message, then the people, who are against you, are evil people.
He recognize that from the beauty of the Ayaat(آيات) of Qur'an and the virtues of Islam.
But then Mafrooq(مفروق) didn't want to take the decision and become a Muslim because he has to consult.
So he said: And here is our religious leader Haani Bin Qubaisah(هاني بن قبيسه)
why don't you get his opinion?
So he pointed towards Hannah(هانه), and said to Rasool Allah ﷺ
why didn't you get his opinion?
Haani Bin Qubaisah(هاني بن قبيسه) said: Yes! What you are calling to, is a noble message.
However, it is not appropriate for us to accept this religion and join it
just because of one meeting that we had with you
that is hastening, and that is unwise,
but we have to go back consult our people, and we will wait, and you wait.
So, he have nothing wrong to say about Islam, but he said:
It's not appropriate for us, just make a decision right here on the spot.
We have to think about it, we have to consult our people,
because we have left some of our leaders, back home.
And then he turned on the attention to Al-Muthana Bin Harissa(المثني بن حارثه).
And he said and here is Al-Muthana Bin Harissa(المثني بن حارثه)
why don't you hear what he has to say?
So, Al-Muthanna Bin Harissa(المثني بن حارثه) said: I agree with what Hannah(هانه) said,
that your message is a noble message.
But we are people who are between two wings
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: What is that?
He said: On one side it is Persia, and on one side is the land of the Arabs.
Bannu Sahibaan(بنوشعيبان) were on the borders of the Persian Empire.
Al-Muthanna Bin Harissa(المثني بن حارثه) said;
Our agreement with the Persians, is that we do not give refuge to anybody who has committed a crime.
And I think that what you are calling to, is something that kings do not like.
Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله) look at the wisdom, and this was just out of one meeting.
He said: I think that what you are calling to, this religion is not something that kings like.
Therefore, we can promise you protection from the side of the Arabs
but we cannot promise you protection from the side of the Persians,
because they do not forgive, this is an empire.
They will be very unforgiving but with the Arabs you can give and take.
Tribes, just like us, but with the Persians, we cannot promise you protection.
So, it was half a deal, it was better than nothing.
Rasool Allah ﷺ in Makkah had nothing, it was a dead end.
Atleast they are willing to give Rasool Allah ﷺ opportunity to make Da'wah(دعوة)
towards one side, but not to the other.
But did Rasool Allah ﷺ takes the offer, or did he refuse it?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
ما أسئل تم الرد
Your response was very nice, very polite
ولكن الهذالأمرلا يقوم إلَّا لِمن أحاطه من كُلِّ جوانب
But this is a religion that cannot stand, unless it is surrounded from every direction.
This is a religion that cannot stand unless you offer it protection from every side.
This issue needs to be protected from every direction.
You cannot offer me protection from one side, and not from the other.
ادْخُلُوا فِي السِّلْمِ كَافَّةً
With Islam, you don't give and take, you don't pick and choose, you take it all.
اللہ عز و جل أغنى الشركاء عن الشرك
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, does not want any partner with Him.
Therefore if you give something to Allah and you give something to someone else.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ refuses that,
because Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ wants you to give everything to Him
all of your heart goes to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, the Muhabbah(محبه) of Allah سبحانه وتعالى.
Therefore, we cannot sacrifice partially
but we have to sacrifice everything for the sake of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
Anyway, that was the end of the conversation,
so Rasool Allah ﷺ left.
Ali Bin Abi Talib(علي بن ابي طالب) says;
ولقد رأيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم سرَّ بما كان من أمري أبي بكر ومعارفته با الناس
And I've seen that Rasool Allah ﷺ was extremely pleased with the conduct of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه,
and his knowledge about people.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was very happy.
I gave you the talk about this conversation, just to show you some of the abilities of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
that were bestowed by Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
The next part of our journey is very critical event in the life of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
and it's also a very critical event in the entire life of the Ummah(أمة),
and that is the Hijrah An-Nabwiyah(هجرة النبويه).
Ayesha رضي الله عنها says and this is in Al-Bukhari(البخاري),
that one day during the heat of noon.
We saw Rasool Allah ﷺ coming to us and he was veiled, he was masked
he had a turban wrapped around his face.
Now Ayesha رضي الله عنها says that Rasool Allah ﷺ would visit us every day once or twice on a daily basis,
but that particular visit was unusual because it was at noon
and at noon in Arabia, because of the heat, people usually take a break, a nap.
Business stops until the climate calms down, and then they go out again.
So, that was a time when there was no one, on the streets of Makkah.
That is when Rasool Allah ﷺ made his visit to Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه so he came in.
Ayesha رضي الله عنها says:
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(ابو بكر الصديق) said:
Rasool Allah ﷺ would not come in this time, unless there's something important going on
أمرٌ جلاً
There's something serious.
So, he went to meet Rasool Allah ﷺ, Rasool Ullah said:
أخرج ما عندك
Empty your house.
Rasool Allah ﷺ had the secret and he wanted the house to be empty.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said:
إنَّما هم أهلك
This is your family
everyone in my house is your family,
consider them to be your family, so your secret is their secret.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: I have been given permission to make Hijrah(هجرة).
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) the first thing he said was
أصُّحبه
Will I be your companion.? Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Yes.
Ayesha رضي الله عنها says, I have never seen a man cry out of happiness like I've seen my father cry, on that day.
Why did Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه cry?
Do you understand the implications of this journey?
This is a journey where you're risking your life.
The least punishment if you're captured with Rasool Allah ﷺ on this journey,
the least punishment is execution.
So, why, he be happy.?
You have no protection whatsoever you know that Quraish(قريش) have the ability to mobilize everyone to search for you.
The chances seem to be very slim it would have been a big deal.
If Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه agreed to go if he said, Well fine, I'll go with you.
That would have been in itself a great achievement.
But for him, not just to agree to go
but to be so happy that he's going with Rasool Allah ﷺ that he cries out of happiness
it is something that is on a different level.
You could be killed in the next few hours you could be dead.
But Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) was so happy, he was crying
because look at how Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) looks at it.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) sees that this is his opportunity to spend over 11 days with Rasool Allah ﷺ,
without anyone being with them just him, and the Messenger of Allah.
11 days for him to drink from the fountain of prophet hood, exclusively.
11 days Rasool Allah ﷺ is spending his entire time with him, night and day with no interruptions whatsoever.
That's why Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) was very happy.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه said;
O Messenger of Allah I have two camels ready.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) has already prepared two camels for this purpose.
So, they hired a guide, non Muslim, Abdullah Ibn Uraiqat(عبدالله ابن عريقت) from Bannu Dail(بنوديل).
And they made an appointment with him.
After three days to meet them at Ghar-E-Thour(غارثور), south of Makkah.
So at the appointed time at night,
Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) left from the back door of the house of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
rather than going north towards Madina, they went south,
and they went into hiding in the cave in Ghar-E-Thour(غارثور).
Now, immediately, a massive search effort was started by Quraish(قريش), in every direction.
And they mobilize all of their forces for the purpose
lurking for Muhammadﷺ and Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
The people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) have already went through a plan on how to deal with Muhammadﷺ
because they knew that Hijrah(هجرة) is eminent, it's coming.
So they were in this gathering, and they were discussing what to do with Muhammadﷺ.
So, Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) came to them in a form of a man and he sat with them.
So one of them said: I think we should throw him in jail.
So, Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) said: No! Iblees(ابليس) said: No.
His letters will get out of jail and his people will spread his message
and eventually they will come to rescue him, that's not a good solution.
Another man said: Well I think that we should exile him.
He said: No! The words of Muhammadﷺ are so sweet.
He's gonna find followers somewhere else and then they will come and invade you.
What else do you have.?
And now it was the turn of Abu Jahal(ابوجهل) to speak.
So, Abu Jahal(ابوجهل) said: Well, I think that we should appoint a strong man from each clan,
and have all of these young men attack Muhammadﷺ, at the same time.
So, when he is killed the blood of Muhammadﷺ gets spread over all of the clans of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
therefore it's impossible for Bannu Hashim(بنوهاشم), to seek revenge for him
because they have to fight everyone else.
Shaytan(شيطان) Iblees(ابليس) said: That's it! That's right opinion! That's what you should do!
So, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says:
وَإِذْ يَمْكُرُ بِكَ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا لِيُثْبِتُوكَ أَوْ يَقْتُلُوكَ أَوْ يُخْرِجُوكَ وَيَمْكُرُونَ وَيَمْكُرُ اللَّهُ وَاللَّهُ خَيْرُ الْمَاكِرِينَ۝
That the people of Kuffr(كفر), Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), they are making Mukr(مكر) they are plotting against you,
to either imprison you, or to kill you or to drive you out of your land,
but they are planning and Allah is planning and Allah is the best of planners.
So, Muhammadﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), were in the cave of Thour(ثور)
while this massive search efforts was going all over.
And they are frantically looking in every direction trying to find Muhammadﷺ and Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
And to show you, how widespread this effort was.
They did reach to Ghar-E-Thour(غارثور) which is south of Makkah.
Now the direction of Madina is north
but they were looking in every direction and this shows you
that the kuffar(كفار) are not going to leave any stone unturned.
They're going to go all over looking for Muhammadﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
They reached to Ghar-E-Thour(غار ثور) and they were standing right on top of Muhammadﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
So, Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه was looking at them and he sees their feet
and he whispers to Muhammadﷺ and says;
O Messenger of Allah, If one of them would just Look down, look beneath their feet they would see us.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says, O Abu Bakr(ابوبكر),
We are two, and Allah is our third.
We are two and Allah is our third.
and that's when Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ revealed.
إِلَّا تَنصُرُوهُ فَقَدْ نَصَرَهُ ٱللَّهُ إِذْ أَخْرَجَهُ ٱلَّذِينَ كَفَرُواْ ثَانِىَ ٱثْنَيْنِ إِذْ هُمَا فِى ٱلْغَارِ إِذْ يَقُولُ لِصَٰحِبِهِۦ لَا تَحْزَنْ إِنَّ ٱللَّهَ مَعَنَا
Translation of the Ayaah(آية), if you do not aid him, Allah has already aided him.
When those, who disbelieved had driven him out as one of two when they were in the cave,
and he said to his companion.
So, Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه is mentioned here, in Qur'an as companion.
Allah has given him, the name of Sahib(صاحب), Sahibihi(صاحبه).
He told his companion, Do not grieve, indeed, Allah is with us.
And Allah sent down his tranquility upon him and supported him with soldiers, you did not see
and made the words of those, who disbelieved the lowest,
while the word of Allah that is the highest and Allah is Exalted in Might and Wise.
وَأَيَّدَهُ بِجُنُودٍ لَمْ تَرَوْهَا
Allah سبحانه وتعالى has supported Muhammadﷺ with soldiers, you did not see.
What are these soldiers.? Allah ho Aalam(الله اعلم),
but one of them could be the spider.
There's a story of the pigeon, but this is weak, the story of the spider is stronger than that.
The people of Quraish(قريش), they made it to the opening of the cave.
And they were about to walk in, but somebody told them no, no, no dont go in.
There's a spider web on the opening of the cave.
If there was anybody in there that spider web would have been torn apart.
So that weak, insignificant fragile spider web kept the enemies of Allah from Muhammadﷺ and Abu Bakr(أبوبكر).
Anything can be a soldier of Allah, anything
water can be a soldier of Allah, that's what, destroyed Firoun(فرعون)
a mosquito can be a soldier of Allah, that destroyed Namrood(نمرود)
the earth could be a soldier of Allah, it swallowed Qaroon(قارون)
wind can be a soldier of Allah, it destroyed Aad(عاد)
lightning could be a soldier of Allah, thunderbolt, it destroyed Thamood(ثمود).
وَمَا يَعْلَمُ جُنُودَ رَبِّكَ إِلَّا هُوَ
No one knows the soldiers of Allah but He.
A Spider web blocked the entrance to the cave.
You could have a concrete wall they would break through it
but the spider web prevented them from going in.
So it's not your weapons and your strength,
it is the Qadar(قدر) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ and His will.
Three days later, Abdullah Bin Oraiqat(عبدالله بن عريقت) came.
Now, during those three days, how did they survive?
Aamir Bin Fuhairah(عامر بن فهيره) would go shepherding with his sheep and goats, in the desert.
And then he would pass by the cave, for them to milk the goats
and it's not suspicious, he's a shepherd, in the desert.
Asma Bint Abi Bakr(اسماء بنت ابي بكر) would bring them food.
And she was called Zaat An-Nataqain(ذات النطاقين) as we mentioned.
Abdullah Ibn Abi Bakr(عبدالله ابن ابي بكر) and look at the family of Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق)
they are all helping.
Abdullah Ibn Abi Bakr(عبدالله ابن ابي بكر) would spend the day time going from one gathering in Makkah to another
gathering intelligence information and he would go and report it at night.
So he will spend the night with Muhammadﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
Now because the people of the desert are very good at following footsteps.
And they could follow the footsteps of Abdullah Ibn Abi Bakr(عبدالله ابن ابي بكر)
he would have Aamir Bin Fuhairah(عامر بن فهيره) with his sheep follow him.
So that, it would erase any marks.
And he would do that on his way to the cave and on his way back, elaborate plan very detailed.
Three days later Abdullah Adh-dhaily Bin Al-Uraiqat(عبدالله الدهلي بن العريقت), a non Muslim guide
brings the two camels, which were raised, or prepared by Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
and they start on the journey, rather than going through the traditional route they followed the coastal line
and they couldn't do that except with this guide, that wasn't a path that they knew.
So he carried them, through this path.
And this journey by the way, happened in the midst of summer
when it was very hot.
So they would travel at night and rest during the daytime.
Now, the people of Madina,
Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله), look at them the people of Makkah, want to push Rasool Allah ﷺ away
and the people of Madina are eagerly waiting for Muhammadﷺ
every day, they would go outside of Madina, waiting for Muhammadﷺ to come
until the sun would become too hot for them they would go back home
every day, they would go in the morning after Fajr(فجر), wait for a few hours
until it becomes too hot, they would go back.
And one of these days they were out there waiting for Muhammadﷺ to come it was becoming very hot,
so they went back on their way back, two men appeared in the horizon dressed in white,
Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) they were dressed in white, brand new clothes.
And they could be seen easily in the desert
because Az-Zubair Bin Awwam(الزبير بن عوام) came back from a business trip, and he met them on his way.
So he gave them these two new sets of clothes.
He gave one to Rasool Allah ﷺ and one to Abu Bakr(أبوبكر), so they came into Madina with new clothes, white clothes.
So, there was a Jew on top of a Palm tree and he had the vantage point so he could see them in the horizon.
So he said: O Arabs, here's the man you're waiting for, he has arrived.
So all of the Sahabah(صحابه) went rushing to their homes
and they picked up their weapons to go out
ceremonial thing carrying their weapons to greet Rasool Allah ﷺ, when he is coming in.
they took it very formally,
they went they took their weapons and they lined up to meet Muhammadﷺ, when he is coming into Madina.
Anas Ibn Malik رضي الله عنه, who is one of the Ansaar(أنْصَار).
He says: I have witnessed two days in Madina
one of them was the best day in Madina, and one of them was the worst day in Madina.
He says, the best day in Madina was the day in which Rasool Allah ﷺ came in
and the worst day in Madina, was the day Rasool Allah ﷺ left us.
Now, they all gathered around Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
Some of them knew Muhammadﷺ and some of them didn't.
So some would go to Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرألصديق), shaking his hand thinking that he is Muhammadﷺ.
It wasn't until the shade moved, because they were under shade.
So the shade moved.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) stood up
and he held a piece of cloth on top of Rasool Allah ﷺ to provide him with shade.
That's when they realized that the one, who's sitting is Muhammadﷺ
that was the sort of friendship that Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) had with Rasool Allah ﷺ
he was also his servant, he would serve him.
So he would stand up in the sun, holding a piece of cloth to give shade to Muhammadﷺ,
no matter what we do
we wouldn't be able to be in the service of Rasool Allah ﷺ like these Sahabah(صحابه) were.
We can try our best, try to make that up by following the way of Muhammadﷺ and doing what he loves.
If you love Muhammadﷺ, you would do, what he loves and that's how he will love you.
SOME LESSONS FROM MADINA, FROM THE HIJRAH(هجرة).
We first of all want to look at the plan,
because unfortunately a lot of our Islamic work lacks that dimension.
And that's not Sunnah(سنة)
Rasool Allah ﷺ visited in an unusual time.
Look at the elaborate planning!
He was covered, to conceal his identity
and during the path to Madina
the people would come and they would speak to Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
and they would tell him, Who is this man with you, he would say,
هذا هاديني الطريق
He's guiding me.
They would understand, he is guiding him through the desert
what he meant, he's guiding him towards Jannah(جنة), towards paradise.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him empty the house.
They left at night, and they left from a back door, they followed an unusual path.
They hired a guide.
Abdullah Ibn Abu Bakr(عبدالله ابن ابوبكر) was gathering intelligence for them.
Asma(اسماء) was bringing them food.
Aamir Bin Fuhairah(عامر بن فهيره) would cover the tracks of Abdullah(عبدالله) and provide them with milk.
All of this was part of the plan.
In terms of hiring the guide, who was non Muslim.
What is the Hukum(حكم) in that.
Shaikh(شيخ) Abil Kareem Zaidan(عابل كريم زيدان), he makes a statement on seeking assistance from the disbelievers.
He says: The general rule is that it's not allowed.
But there is an exception that is made when the following rules apply.
Number one, the existence of a strong need to seek this assistance.
Number two, that this assistance not be at the expense,
or compromise of Daw'ah(دعوة) or any of its meanings.
Number three, that there exists a satisfactory level of trust in the disbeliever.
And finally, that it won't cause doubts among the Muslims.
If these rules apply, then it will be allowed to seek assistance from a disbeliever
and the scholars would add another rule,  that they do not have the upper hand.
But the Muslims have the upper hand and the leadership in the situation.
SOME LESSONS FROM THE HIJRAH(هجرة).
Number one, the elaborate organization of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
now Rasool Allah ﷺ was a Nabi(نبي) from Allah.
Maybe he didn't need to follow all of these rules
but Rasool Allah ﷺ is teaching us that this is Sunnah(سنة).
This is how, you do things, this is the right way
He is our example, and if he is the Messenger of Allah
whom we would expect that Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ would protect and save.
وَاللَّهُ يَعْصِمُكَ مِنَ النَّاسِ
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ told Muhammadﷺ, I will protect you from your enemies
he was guaranteed protection from Allah.
Nevertheless, he went through this elaborate planning very detailed and worked it out to tell us
that this is my Sunnah(سنة) and this is my way.
And you're breaking my Sunnah(سنة), if we don't do it, this way.
Now, just as Allah سبحانه تعالى has laws of nature.
See Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has created laws.
We call laws of nature but there really are laws of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
And Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says about laws,
وَلَنْ تَجِدَ لِسُنَّتِ اللَّهِ تَحْوِيلً
You will not find any change to the laws of Allah
they will not change, they are standard.
If you bring oxygen, and hydrogen, you mix them together
you're going to get water, you're not gonna get nitrogen
you will always get water.
That's a law of Allah, it will never breaks, it never changes.
Now just as there are laws of Allah in the natural world
there are laws of Allah that govern our lives as individuals, as societies
as nations laws that govern battles, laws that govern everything
everything is governed by laws.
Rasool Allah ﷺ is telling us that no one can go against these laws of Allah.
Even if I do, you have to go along with the laws of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ and not go against them, not try to break them,
because there's no favoritism here,
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will not give you a favor over a disbeliever just because you are Muslim.
Rasool Allah ﷺ had to prepare
everyone has to seek Rizq(رزق).
Is there any exemption in Qur'an
that says that by being Muslim, you don't have to seek Rizq(رزق)?
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will make raindrops made of gold fall on top of you.?
There's no exception to the rule, just like the Kafir(كافر) has to go to seek Rizq(رزق)
you have to go out and seek Rizq(رزق),
the birds have to go out and seek Rizq(رزق)
the beast have to go out and seek Rizq(رزق)
there's no exception from the rule, the law of Allah is standard
it applies to everyone.
So we shouldn't think that a spontaneous unprepared effort will be rewarded.
Just because we Muslims, and Allah needs to do us a favor.
ليس بأمانيكم
It's not according to your desires.
That's the first lesson, number two, Planning ahead.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه did not know yet that he will make Hijrah(حجرة) with Rasool Allah ﷺ
he suspected that he might be the companion of Rasool Ullah but he had no guarantees,
until the last moment he didn't know, Rasool Allah ﷺ kept it as a secret.
Nevertheless, Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه purchased his two camels
and he feeds them special meal.
ورقع السُمر
The leaves of a certain plant which was expensive but it makes the camel strong.
He was feeding them that expensive food,
because he thought one day maybe I will have a chance to be the companion of Rasool Allah ﷺ on Hijrah(هجرة).
It could be in a month, it could be in a year, it can be 10 years there was no gurantee, whatsoever
but he still planned ahead.
You see it's not easy to plan ahead.
When you don't even know what's gonna happen.?
But, Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) did that
and notice that Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ in the Battle of Tabook(تبوك),
the Munafiqeen(منافقين) they came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said;
Someone would come and say, O Messenger of Allah,
I cannot join you in the Battle of Tabook(تبوك) because of this reason
which sounded as a valid reason.
Another Munafiq(منافق) would come and say:
O Messenger of Allah I cannot join you in the battle, because of this reason which also sounded like a good excuse.
And they kept on coming to Rasool Allah ﷺ
and Rasool Allah ﷺ excused them.
He gave them excuse, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, said;
عَفَا اللَّهُ عَنكَ لِمَ أَذِنتَ لَهُمْ
May Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, forgive you.
Why did you give them permission?
And then Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ said;
وَلَوْ أَرَادُوا الْخُرُوجَ لَأَعَدُّوا لَهُ عُدَّةً
If they were serious in their intentions of marching out
they would have made prior preparations for it.
They waited until the last moment and yes they had some unfinished business
but Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says, if they did have the intention to go out
they would have prepared for it, in advance.
وَلَٰكِن كَرِهَ ٱللَّهُ ٱنبِعَاثَهُمْ فَثَبَّطَهُمْ
But Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ did not want them to go out, these are Munafiqeen(منافقين), they didn't deserve it.
So you have to be ready, you have to be prepared.
The problem is that we wait until the last moment, we cannot do the thing.
And then we think that we are exempted
if you had a chance to finish that unfinished business before and you didn't
you're going to be held responsible.
We have to take Islam seriously, we can just leave it like that spontaneously and think that things will work out.
The third lesson, you noticed that the whole plan of Hijrah(هجرة) was secret
shrouded in secrecy, everything was done in secret.
Rasool Allah ﷺ did both in his life there was a public stage and there was a secret stage
and that's important for the Daw'ah(دعوة).
In some situations, things will get strict and severe and difficult.
So, you have to go underground.
And only Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ knows what the future is holding.
I mean, for example, when you read the Ahadith(احاديث) of Al-Fittan(فتن) in the time of Al-Mahdi(المهدي).
When it says that only 300 will give him Baiyah(بيعة).
Is that all the people in the Muslim world, who want to give Baiyah(بيعة)
it must have been a secret Baiyah(بيعة).
Otherwise, they would have been masses of people, who are involved.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ talks about the armies that will be in Iraq
and will be in the Sham(ألشام) and will be in Yemen
you can imply from the text that there's a lot of underground work that is going on.
It's not all public,
and a time might come, when the work must be done through secret organized orders that are very small in number
and the profile of such people will be youth, who are dedicated to serve Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ like Ahlal-Kahf(اهل الكهف).
These were young men, who fleed from persecution in secret,
but they were a group, they went in to hiding in the cave
and notice that this is the exact Surah(سورة) we are told to recite when Ad-Dajjal(الدجال) comes out.
And it's particularly the first Ayaat(آيات) of Surat Ul Kahaf(سورةالكهف) which are talking about the youth of the cave.
Because this was a Muslim group, tight knit, all young dedicated willing to sacrifice for Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
They had to run away from the persecution and go in a hiding.
But the thing is that both is Sunnah(سنة).
According to the circumstances, there's public work, and there's secret work
because we know that there's a lot of enemies of Islam out there
Shaytan(شيطان) definitely wants to get you.
So, you need to fight the plan of Shaytan(شيطان) with another plan.
You have to cure the disease with the antidote.
Shaytan(شيطان) has poison you have to have the antidote to that particular poison.
Allahعزَّوَجل didn't have to create Shaytan(شيطان).
But he did it, as part of the test
What's the use of having a test because our life in Duniyah(دنيا) is a test.
وَنَبْلُوكُمْ بِالشَّرِّ وَالْخَيْرِ فِتْنَةً
To test you, with both good and evil.
What's the use in having a test if you only have the option of good.
If you are going to be tested, whether you're going to be good or bad
as part of the rules of the test, you have to be given both choices.
So Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has also given you the choice of good
and Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has also given you the choice of evil that's part of the test.
وَنَبْلُوكُمْ بِالشَّرِّ وَالْخَيْرِ فِتْنَة
To test you by good and by evil.
Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه they settled in Madina.
Now brothers and sisters, Al-Muhajiroon(المهاجرون) came from Makkah(مكه),
the most beloved land to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
Rasool Allah ﷺ before he left Makkah,
He stood in a place called Hazwarah(حزورة),
Rasool Allah ﷺ stood in Hazwarah(حزورة) and he looked at Makkah his last view of Makkah.
And he said:
ولله إنكي لخيروأرض الله و أحب أرض الله إلى الله ، ولو لا أنِّي أخرجتُ مِنكِي ما خرج
He says, In the name of Allah, you are the best land of Allah
and you are the most beloved land of Allah to Allah
and if it wasn't for your people driving me out I would never have left.
Leaving Makkah was not easy, it wasn't an easy thing for Rasool Allah ﷺ nor was it easy for Sahabah رضي الله عنهم.
This was the sacred land this is where Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) was.
And whoever sees Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) and goes around the Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) becomes attached to Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
A Mo'min(مؤمن), who has Eeman(إيمان) in their heart, if they go around the Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
Whenever they leave, they would feel homesick.
And Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says in Qur'an because you see, this was the Du'a(دعا) of Ibrahim(ابراهيم).
Ibraheem عليه السّلام made Dua(دعا) to Allah, put the love of this place in the hearts of people.
Because when Ibraheem عليه السّلام, when he left his son, Ismail عليه السّلام and his mother Hajar(هاجر)
and he left there was nobody living there.
So Ibraheem عليه السّلام made Dua(دعا),
فَاجْعَلْ أَفْئِدَةً مِّنَ النَّاسِ تَهْوِي إِلَيْهِمْ
And make the hearts of people go towards them.
So now all the hearts are attached to Makkah.
And when he built Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ made another command to Ibrahim(ابراهيم).
He told him, make Azaan(اذان) to Al-Hajj(الحج), call the people to Al-Hajj(الحج).
Ibrahim عليه السّلام is standing in the desert, there's no one around him, except Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه)
and Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ is telling him to call the people.
So Ibraheem عليه السّلام said, and who will hear me my voice will not reach to the people, there's no one around.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ told him, you make the call, and I will convey the message
you just make the call and I will convey the message.
Well the message was conveyed the invitation of Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) was given to us through Qur'an.
So the words of Ibraheem عليه السّلام have reached millions and millions of people actually billions.
All what Ibraheem(ابراهيم) had to do, is make the call عليه السلام.
And Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ conveyed it to us.
So, they loved Makkah and for the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) this was extremely difficult to leave Makkah.
In addition to that, Al-Madina wasn't a very pleasant place.
It was described as having a lot of stagnant water
when floods would come, they would stagnate,
and the water would become very smelly and it was very epidemic.
A lot of disease breakouts in Al-Madina an endemic environment.
Now the people of Madina grew up in there, so they were used to it
and their bodies developed resistance to those diseases.
But with Al-Muhajireen(المهاجرين), when they came in, they fell sick
and they got this very severe fever
modern scholars say that it might have been malaria
because of the existence of stagnant water and all of that it could have been malaria breakouts but Allah ho Alam(الله اعلم).
It was described in our books of Seerah(سيرة), in history as fever breakouts.
I just want you to imagine, with Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) or any one of the Sahabah(صحابه)
feeling homesick alright and what a painful feeling that is homesick to Makkah.
You're separated from your families
and then you become sick and ill, and if there's no one to care for you from your family,
and you're not staying in your house, you've left your bed, and you're a foreigner.
Can you imagine how difficult those feelings are?
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) was living with Bilal(بلال) and Aamir Bin Fuhairah(عامر بن فهيره) his servant.
They were sharing the same room.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told Ayesha(عائشه), O Ayesha(عائشه) go and take care of them.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has blessed Muhammadﷺ, he didn't get affected with that fever.
But the other Muhajireen(مهاجرين) and they were going through it.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ told Ayesha(عائشه) go and take care of them.
He felt for his Sahabah(الصحابه) and he cared about them a lot.
So Ayesha رضي الله عنها says, I went there and this was before Al-Hijab(حجاب).
So I went there and I walked up to my father and I said;
يا ابتي كيف تجدك؟
O my father, How are you doing.?
So, my father responded by a line of poetry and he said:
كُلٌ مرِعٍ أصبحٌ في أهله والموت أدْنى مِشراكٍ أليه
He said, Every one of us is spending their day while death could be closer to them than the strap on their shoes,
the strap of their shoes means it's very close to you he was talking about death.
Ayesha رضي الله عنها said: My father doesn't know, what he's saying.
The fever was so bad it was causing hallucinations.
You can imagine how severe the fever was.
She said;
أبي لا يعقل ما يبقي
My father doesn't know what he's saying.
And then she went to Aamir Bin Fuhairah(عامر بن فهيره) and she said:
Aamir(عامر)! How are you.?
So he responded by saying,
لقد وجدت الموت  قبل زوقيه إنَّ جبعنا حتْفهو من فوقه
I've seen death before I could taste it and even the coward will eventually die.
She said, and Aamir(عامر) doesn't know, what he's saying.
And then she said: She went to Bilal(بلال) and she asked him, how were you doing
and she said he was unconscious and whenever he would regain consciousness,
he would sit up in the middle of the room
he would sit in the middle of the room, and speak to himself
and he would raise his voice by saying:
ألا ليلة شهري هل أبيتنَّ ليلةً
بوادٍ وحولي إزخَرًا وجليلُ
وهل أردنا يومًا مياحه مجنةٍ وهل يبدوانَّ لي شامةٌ وطفيلُ
He said: We'll I ever spend a night in a valley surrounded by Izkhar(ازخر) and Jalil(جليل).
Izkhar(ازخر) and Jalil(جليل) are two plants that grow in Makkah.
He said: Will there ever come a time, when I would spend my night
in a valley surrounded by Izkhar(ازخر) and Jalil(جليل)
and will I ever visit the waters of Majannah(مجنة) in Makkah
and will I ever see Shaama(شامه) and Tafeel(طفيل), two mountains in Makkah
feeling homesick to Makkah - Bilal رضي الله عنه.
And he's raising his voice with these lines of poetry
Ayesha رضي الله عنها, she went back to Muhammadﷺ
and told him what was happening, Rasool Allah ﷺ cried.
Because Rasool Allah ﷺ was the one, who brought them here.
They sacrificed their homes, they sacrifice their families.
They left Makkah and they came to a foreign land suffered from diseases, they did that for Muhammadﷺ.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ cried. And then he made the Dua(دعا)
اللهم حبب إلينا المدينةَ كحبنا مكة أو أشدَّ حبَّا،
أللهم باركلنا في مدِّها وسعيها وأنقل هُمَّاحا إلى جهفة
In Bukhari(بخاري) Rasool Allah ﷺ made this Dua(دعا) and said;
O Allah make us love Madina, like we love Makkah or more.
And O Allah make it's blessed and O Allah take the fever of it,
out of the Madina and put it in Al-Juhffah(جهفه).
How did Makkah become blessed?
Through the Dua(دعا) of Ibraheem عليه السّلام.
Al-Madina at that moment had nothing special to it
but Rasool Allah ﷺ made this Dua(دعا) to bless Madina
and Rasool Allah ﷺ made the Dua(دعا) to make it more beloved to us than Makkah.
And since then every believer loves Madina more than Makkah.
If you visited Makkah and Madina when you get inside Madina you have this completely different feeling,
tranquility is in the air.
It is the Barakah(بركة) of the Dua(دعا) of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
اللهم حبب إلينا المدينةَ كحبنا مكة أو أشدَّ حبَّا،
And it's in fact the sign of Eeman(ايمان) to love Al-Madina.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه and the Sahabah(صحابه) who were crying and longing to go back to Makkah
never went back even when they had the chance to do so.
And when Makkah was opened they all went back with Rasool Allah ﷺ to Al-Madina
and Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) chose it to be, his capital
and so did Umar Ibn Khattab(عمر إبن خطاب) and so did Uthman رضي الله عنهم.
And if it wasn't for the circumstances that forced Ali(علي) out
he would have remained in there too, رضي الله عنه ، رضي الله عن صحابه اجمعين.
وصلوات الله ولسلام علي سيد الأولين والآخرين والحمدلله رب العلمين